{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "1.7","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Folic acid deficiency","Sideroblastic anemia","IDA","Hemolytic anemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "IDA","explanation": "The most common treatment modality utilized in PV is phlebotomy. Reduction of blood volume (usually 1 unit of whole blood—450 cc) can be performed weekly or even twice weekly in younger patients to control symptoms. The Hct target range is less than 45% for men and less than 42% for women. IDA is a predictable complication of therapeutic phlebotomy because approximately 250 mg of iron is removed with each unit of blood"},"question": "Repeated phlebotomy in patients with PV may lead to the development of:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Anemia/2"},{"choices": ["Increased in number and functionally abnormal","Normal in number and functionally abnormal","Decreased in number and functional","Decreased in number and functionally abnormal"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Increased in number and functionally abnormal","explanation": "In ET, the PLT count is extremely elevated. These PLTs are abnormal in function, leading to both bleeding and thrombotic diathesis"},"question": "In ET, the PLTs are:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/CBCs/Platelets/2"},{"choices": ["Niemann–Pick cells","Reactive lymphocytes","Flame cells","Reed–Sternberg (RS) cells"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Reed–Sternberg (RS) cells","explanation": "The morphological common denominator in Hodgkin lymphoma is the RS cell. It is a large, binucleated cell with a dense nucleolus surrounded by clear space. These characteristics give the RS cell an “owl’s eye” appearance. Niemann–Pick cells (foam cells) are histiocytes containing phagocytized sphingolipids that stain pale blue and impart a foamlike texture to the cytoplasm. Flame cells are plasma cells with a distinctive red cytoplasm. They are sometimes seen in the bone marrow of patients with multiple myeloma"},"question": "Which of the following cells is considered pathognomonic for Hodgkin disease?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Lymphoma/1"},{"choices": ["Target cells","Schistocytes","Teardrop-shaped cells","Ovalocytes"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Teardrop-shaped cells","explanation": "The marked amount of fibrosis, both medullary and extramedullary, accounts for the irreversible change in RBC morphology to a teardrop shape. The RBCs are “teared” as they attempt to pass through the fibrotic tissue"},"question": "In myelofibrosis, the characteristic abnormal RBC morphology is that of:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/RBC microscopic morphology/1"},{"choices": ["Increased plasma volume","Pancytopenia","Decreased O2 saturation","Absolute increase in total RBC mass"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Absolute increase in total RBC mass","explanation": "The diagnosis of PV requires the demonstration of an increase in RBC mass. Pancytosis may also be seen in about two thirds of PV cases. Plasma volume is normal or slightly reduced, and arterial O2 saturation is usually normal"},"question": "PV is characterized by:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/RBCs/Leukemias/2"},{"choices": ["Splenomegaly","Decreased O2 saturation","Increased RBC mass","Increased erythropoietin"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Splenomegaly","explanation": "Splenomegaly is a feature of PV but not characteristic of secondary polycythemia. The RBC mass is increased in both primary polycythemia (PV) and secondary polycythemia. Erythropoietin is increased, and O2 saturation is decreased in secondary polycythemia"},"question": "Features of secondary polycythemia include all of the following except:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/RBC disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Decreased arterial O2 saturation","Decreased plasma volume of circulating blood","Increased erythropoietin levels","Increased erythropoiesis in bone marrow"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Decreased plasma volume of circulating blood","explanation": "Relative polycythemia is caused by reduction of plasma, rather than an increase in RBC volume or mass. RBC mass is increased in both PV and secondary polycythemia, but erythropoietin levels are high only in secondary polycythemia"},"question": "Erythrocytosis in relative polycythemia occurs because of:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/RBC disorders/2"},{"choices": ["Panmyelosis","Pancytosis","Pancytopenia","Panhyperplasia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Pancytosis","explanation": "PV is a myeloproliferative disorder characterized by uncontrolled proliferation of erythroid precursors. However, production of all cell lines is usually increased. Panhyperplasia is a term used to describe the cellularity of bone marrow in PV"},"question": "In PV, what is characteristically seen in peripheral blood?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Polycythemia/1"},{"choices": ["100", "117", "137", "252"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "137","explanation": "One hundred mature neutrophils are counted and scored. The LAP score is calculated as follows: (the number of 1+ cells × 1) + (2+ cells × 2) + (3+ cells × 3) + (4+ cells × 4). That is, 48 + 76 + 9 + 4 = 137. The reference range is approximately 20 to 130"},"question": "Leukocyte alkaline phosphatase (LAP) staining performed on a patient gives the following results: 10(0) 48(1+) 38(2+) 3(3+) 1(4+) Calculate the LAP score.","reference": "Hematology/Calculate/LAP score/2"},{"choices": ["CML: low LAP; leukemoid: high LAP","CML: high LAP; leukemoid: low LAP","CML: high WBC; leukemoid: normal WBC","CML: high WBC; leukemoid: higher WBC"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "CML: low LAP; leukemoid: high LAP","explanation": "CML causes a low LAP score, whereas an elevated or normal score occurs in a leukemoid reaction. CML cannot be distinguished by WBC count because both CML and leukemoid reaction have a high count"},"question": "CML is distinguished from leukemoid reaction by which of the following?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory and clinical data to specify additional tests/Leukemias/2"},{"choices": ["Myeloid metaplasia","Leukoerythroblastosis","Fibrosis of bone marrow","All of these options"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All of these options","explanation": "Anemia, fibrosis, myeloid metaplasia, thrombocytosis, and leukoerythroblastosis occur in IMF"},"question": "Which of the following occurs in idiopathic myelofibrosis (IMF)?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Myeloproliferative neoplasms/3"},{"choices": ["It is not predictive","The prognosis is better if Ph1 is present","The prognosis is worse if Ph1 is present","The disease usually transforms into AML when Ph1 is present"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The prognosis is better if Ph1 is present","explanation": "Ninety percent of patients with CML have the Ph1 chromosome. This appears as a long-arm deletion of chromosome 22 but is actually a translocation between the long arms of chromosomes 22 and 9. The ABL oncogene from chromosome 9 forms a hybrid gene with the bcr region of chromosome 22. This results in production of a chimeric protein with tyrosine kinase activity that activates the cell cycle. The prognosis for CML is better if the Ph1 chromosome is present. Often, a second chromosomal abnormality occurs in CML before a blast crisis"},"question": "What influence does the Philadelphia (Ph1) chromosome have on the prognosis of patients with CML?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Genetic theory and principles/CML/2"},{"choices": ["Many teardrop-shaped cells","Intense LAP staining","A decrease in granulocytes","An increase in basophils"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "An increase in basophils","explanation": "CML is marked by an elevated WBC count demonstrating various stages of maturation, hypermetabolism, and minimal LAP staining. An increase in basophils and eosinophils is a common finding. Pseudo–Pelger–Huët cells and thrombocytosis may be present. Bone marrow is hypercellular, with a high M:E ratio (e.g., 10:1)"},"question": "Which of the following is (are) commonly found in CML?","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/CML/3"},{"choices": ["Leukemoid reactions", "IMF", "PV", "CML"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "CML","explanation": "CML shows the least LAP activity, whereas the LAP score is slightly to markedly increased in each of the other states"},"question": "In which of the following conditions does LAP show the least activity?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/LAP score/1"},{"choices": ["Profusion of bizarre blast cells","Normal number of typical granulocytes","Presence of granulocytes at different stages of development","Pancytopenia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Presence of granulocytes at different stages of development","explanation": "The WBC count in CML is often higher than 100 × 109/L, and the peripheral blood smear shows granulocyte progression from myeloblast to segmented neutrophil"},"question": "A striking feature of the peripheral blood of a patient with CML is:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/WBCs/CML/2"},{"choices": ["Infections","WBCs greater than 20.0 × 109/L","Hemorrhage","Splenomegaly"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Splenomegaly","explanation": "Splenomegaly is seen in greater than 90% of patients with CML, but it is not a characteristic finding in AML. Infections, hemorrhage, and elevated WBC counts may be seen in both CML and AML"},"question": "Which of the following is often associated with CML but not with AML?","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/CML/Characteristics/2"},{"choices": ["Monoclonal gammopathy","Hyperviscosity of blood","Bence–Jones protein in urine","Osteolytic lesions"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Osteolytic lesions","explanation": "Osteolytic lesions indicating destruction of bone, as evidenced by radiography, are seen in multiple myeloma but not in Waldenström macroglobulinemia. In addition, Waldenström macroglobulinemia gives rise to lymphocytosis, which does not occur in multiple myeloma, and differs in the morphology of the malignant cells"},"question": "Multiple myeloma and Waldenström macroglobulinemia have all of the following in common except:","reference": "Hematology/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize health and disease states/Myeloma/Characteristics/2"},{"choices": ["Microcytic hypochromic cells","Intracellular inclusion bodies","Rouleaux","Hypersegmented neutrophils"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Rouleaux","explanation": "Rouleaux is present in patients with multiple myeloma as a result of increased viscosity and decreased albumin:globulin ratio. Multiple myeloma is a plasma cell dyscrasia that is characterized by overproduction of monoclonal immunoglobulin"},"question": "What is the characteristic finding seen in the peripheral blood smear from a patient with multiple myeloma?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Myeloma/Microscopic morphology/1"},{"choices": ["Marrow plasmacytosis","Lytic bone lesions","Serum and/or urine M component (monoclonal protein)","Ph1 chromosome"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Ph1 chromosome","explanation": "The Ph1 chromosome is a diagnostic marker for CML. Osteolytic lesions, monoclonal gammopathy, and bone marrow infiltration by plasma cells constitute the triad of diagnostic markers for multiple myeloma"},"question": "All of the following are associated with the diagnosis of multiple myeloma except:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/Myeloma/2"},{"choices": ["CLL","Acute myelogenous leukemia","Benign monoclonal gammopathy","Benign adenoma"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Benign monoclonal gammopathy","explanation": "Benign monoclonal gammopathies have peripheral blood findings similar to those in myeloma. However, a lower concentration of monoclonal protein is usually seen. There are no osteolytic lesions, and the plasma cells comprise less than 10% of nucleated cells in bone marrow. About 30% become malignant, and therefore the term monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS) is the designation used to describe this condition"},"question": "Multiple myeloma is most difficult to distinguish from:","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Myeloma/2"},{"choices": ["Expanding plasma cell mass","Overproduction of monoclonal immunoglobulins","Production of osteoclast activating factor (OAF) and other cytokines","All of these options"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All of these options","explanation": "Mutated plasmablasts in bone marrow undergo clonal replication and expand the plasma cell mass. Normal bone marrow is gradually replaced by malignant plasma cells, leading to pancytopenia. Most malignant plasma cells actively produce immunoglobulins. In multiple myeloma, the normally controlled and purposeful production of antibodies is replaced by inappropriate production of even larger amounts of useless immunoglobulin molecules. The normally equal production of light chains and heavy chains may be imbalanced. The result is the release of excess free light chains or free heavy chains. The immunoglobulins produced by a single clone of myeloma cells are identical. Any abnormal production of identical antibodies is referred to by the general term monoclonal gammopathy. Osteoclasts are bone cells active in locally resorbing bone and releasing calcium into blood. Nearby osteoblasts are equally active in utilizing the calcium in blood to form new bone. Multiple myeloma interrupts this balance by the secretion of at least two substances. These are interleukin-6 (IL-6) and OAF. As its name implies, OAF stimulates osteoclasts to increase bone resorption and release of calcium, which lead to lytic lesions of the bone"},"question": "The pathology of multiple myeloma includes which of the following?","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Immunologic manifestation of disease/Immunoglobulins/2"},{"choices": ["Lymphoplasmacytoid cells","Adrenal cortex","Myeloblastic cell lines","Erythroid cell precursors"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Lymphoplasmacytoid cells","explanation": "Waldenström macroglobulinemia is a malignancy of lymphoplasmacytoid cells, which manufacture IgM. Although the cells secrete immunoglobulin, they are not fully differentiated into plasma cells and lack the characteristic perinuclear halo, deep basophilia, and eccentric nucleus characteristic of classic plasma cells"},"question": "Waldenström macroglobulinemia is a malignancy of the:","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Immunologic manifestation of disease/2"},{"choices": ["Infectious mononucleosis","Infectious lymphocytosis","Hairy cell leukemia (HCL)","T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Hairy cell leukemia (HCL)","explanation": "A variable number of malignant cells in HCL will stain positive with tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase (TRAP+). Although this cytochemical reaction is fairly specific for HCL, TRAP activity has occasionally been reported in B-cell leukemia and, rarely, T- cell leukemia"},"question": "Cells that exhibit positive staining with acid phosphatase and are not inhibited by tartaric acid are characteristically seen in:","reference": "Hematology/Apply principles of special procedures/Cytochemical stains/2"},{"choices": ["ET", "IMF", "PV", "CML"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "CML","explanation": "The JAK2(V617F) mutation is negative in patients with CML. It may be positive in patients with IMF (35%–57%), PV (65%–97%), and ET (23%–57%)"},"question": "The JAK2(V617F) mutation may be positive in all of the following chronic myeloproliferative disorders except:","reference": "Hematology/Correlate clinical and laboratory data/CML/Characteristics/3"},{"choices": ["PLT count 450 × 109/L or greater","Megakaryocyte proliferation with large and mature morphology and no or little granulocyte or erythroid proliferation","Demonstration of JAK2(V617F) or other clonal marker","Evidence of clonality"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Evidence of clonality","explanation": "In the revised 2016 WHO classification, diagnosis of ET requires meeting four major WHO diagnostic criteria, which include: PLT count 450 × 109/L or greater; bone marrow proliferation of megakaryocyte lineage with large and mature megakaryocytes with hyperlobulated nuclei and no or little granulocyte or erythroid proliferation; not meeting WHO criteria for CML, PV, PMF, MDS, or other myeloid neoplasm; and demonstration of JAK2(V617F), CALR, or MPL mutation or other clonal marker. Diagnosis can also be made with the first three major criteria and one minor criterion, either evidence of clonality or absence of reactive thrombocytosis"},"question": "All of the following are major criteria for the 2008 WHO diagnostic criteria for ET except:","reference": "Hematology/Apply knowledge of special procedures/Myeloproliferative diseases/Classifications/3"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Lymphoproliferative and Myeloproliferative Disorders"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}